Good morning, today's דף daf, *daf* is מ"ח *Mem-Ches* (48). We pick
up actually in the middle of מ"ח *Mem-Ches*. Two lines in the
wide lines, ועוד *ve-od*.
And the issue is, for people who have a bit losing track
about what we've been talking about,
the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* spoke about how you take חלה Challah *challah*
from dough that is טמא Tamei. *tamei* on פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, since
you shouldn't be allowed to bake it since you can't eat it,
but you can't not bake it because it'll become חמץ Chametz? *chametz*.
And there was a debate. One opinion basically said you bake it
and then you call it חלה Challah... *challah*, so when you're baking
it, it's not yet חלה Challah *challah*, it's not yet a problem.
And the other said you don't have to worry, that was רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer*. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*
said you don't have to worry about it because this is not
חמץ Chametz. *chametz* that you transgress because it is הקדש *hekdesh* or
a type of a הקדש *hekdesh* and it's not considered to be
yours. We are in about a minute going to circle back to
that debate, because one of the issues of course around that is,
can you bake this bread on יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov*
if you know that a certain percent of it you're not going
to be able to eat, that it's going to in the end
you're going to take it as חלה Challah *challah*, which is רבי
אליעזר'ס *Rabbi Eliezer's* position. So as a lead-up to that, we have
been focusing on a very important debate of רבא Rava, *Rava* and
רב חסדא Rav Chisda? *Rav Chisda*. If somebody cooks from יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov* to the weekday, does a person get lashes?
Where רבא *Rava* says no, because he has a principle of הואיל
Ho'il. *ho'il*, which means hypothetically, I'll translate it, literally means since, but
hypothetically you could eat it now if a lot of guests dropped
by, it would be able to be eaten. So even though that
was not the reason why you cooked it, it's considered to be
צורך יום טוב Yom Tov *tzorech Yom Tov* because it could be
eaten now on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. And רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*
says no, it has to only be if your intention is to
eat on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, not if your intention is to
eat it afterwards, otherwise you would get lashes. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
although we understood that רבא'ס *Rava's* idea of הואיל Ho'il *ho'il* would
be a way to give a little greater latitude to an act
of cooking, which is fundamentally a permissible act on יום טוב *Yom
Tov*, at least in a challenge that רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* had
to רבא *Rava*—we don't know how רבא *Rava* himself would have responded—he
said, well, by that logic, if you dug a furrow on יום
טוב *Yom Tov*, you should be exempt because there's a way that
that furrow would be allowed. It wasn't exactly clear why that would
be true, to use the dirt to cover the blood of a
chicken that you שחט *shechted*, but that wouldn't allow you to dig
a furrow on יום טוב *Yom Tov* anyway. He assumed you could
apply this hypothetical scenario even to something which is fundamentally not an
act of food preparation. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* dealt with it
as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did, but the more immediate pressing issue
of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is another משנה Mishnah *mishna* that teaches
that there's a way to get five lashes in the process of
cooking a גיד הנשה *gid hanasheh* on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, if
it's a גיד הנשה *gid hanasheh*, בשר בחלב *basar bechalav*, dot dot
dot. And one of the things is that you're making a fire
on יום טוב *Yom Tov* without a legitimate purpose. And the question
here was the same. According to you רבא *Rava*, that you say
hypothetically there's a legitimate use, well hypothetically even if you're making the
fire for cooking this גיד הנשה *gid hanasheh*, you could use the
fire for other things, and you shouldn't get lashes on that. And
that actually was a question I would think that would resonate with
us because we actually know that we do give a lot of
latitude for making a fire on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, even if
it's not really serving any, you know, greater purpose. So that was
his question: Why do you get lashes therefore, according to you, for
the fire the same way you don't get lashes for doing the
cooking, because hypothetically it serves a purpose. And the answer was, you're
right. Take out that line in the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* that said
that the lashes is for making a fire, we have to replace
it with getting lashes for something else. What was the something else?
So the most recent else that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was dealing
with, thank you very much, is מוקצה *muktzah*. That it was מוקצה
*muktzah* wood. And assuming that מוקצה *muktzah* was דאורייתא *de-oraita*—the idea—and therefore
you can't say theoretically you could have used the מוקצה *muktzah* wood
for something else because it's מוקצה *muktzah*, there's nothing else you could
use it for. It's not like a fire which you can do
for legitimate purposes. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rejects it. It says
מוקצה *muktzah* is not דאורייתא *de-oraita*, and therefore that would not be
a good reason. ועוד *ve-od*, and here we pick up two lines
down into the wide lines, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, in addition,
את הוא דאמרת *at-hu de-amart*
חילוק מלאכות דשבת ואין חילוק מלאכות דיום
טוב *chiluk melachos de-Shabbos ve-ein chiluk melachos de-Yom Tov*. That there's a
distinction of מלאכות *melachos* for שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and not for יום
טוב *Yom Tov*. What it means is that if a person were
to do different categories of מלאכה Melacha, *melacha*, one each of the
39 מלאכות *melachos* on שבת *Shabbos*, they would have to bring 39
sin offerings.
If however you did two of the same מלאכה Melacha *melacha*, it
would only be one sin offering. But the purpose of different categories
for שבת *Shabbos* is to say that you can bring up to
that amount of sin offerings if you did it בשוגג *be-shogeg*. But
on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, if you actually did two מלאכות *melachos*
on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, first you made a furrow and then
you planted a seed—right? Because we also have the 39 מלאכות *melachos*,
but there's no sin offering on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because you
only bring a sin offering on something that you would get כרת
kares. *kareis* or you would get a death penalty for. So the
only issue of having different categories would be, would you get different
sets of lashes if you did it במזיד *be-meizid*. So if on
יום טוב *Yom Tov* במזיד *be-meizid* I dug a furrow and then
I planted the seed, so you says otherwise... who says that you
don't get two sets of lashes. When you're dealing with sin offerings,
the by שבת *Shabbat*, the purpose of thirty-nine categories is you could
say if you did it בשוגג *Beshogeg* you bring up to thirty-nine
sin offerings, but by יום טוב *Yom Tov* no sin offerings and
all we're dealing with is if you did it intentionally and getting
lashes, then it's all the same איסור *Issur*, doing a מלאכה Melacha
*Melachah*. And therefore, doing a מלאכה *Melachah* on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
you're
not חייב מיתה *Chayav Mita*? No.
יום טוב *Yom
Tov* is only a לא תעשה *Lo Ta'aseh* and an עשה *Aseh*.
It's not כרת karet, *Karet*, it's not מיתה *Mita*. So therefore the
only relevance of your transgression in terms of practical implications in this
world, besides how you get punished up in שמים *Shamayim*, is the
issue of lashes. Well, he says, then we don't consider it thirty-nine
separate prohibitions. It's one prohibition and even if you did the same
way if you did... dug thirty-nine, you know, furrows, you'd only get
one set of lashes. If you dug a furrow and planted something
and watered and pruned and whatever, you only get one set of
lashes. It's the same prohibition that you did multiple times. So therefore
that cannot be what this משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* says when it says
that you get five lashes for cooking this גיד הנשה *Gid HaNasheh*
because you're already getting a set of lashes, a ברייתא Braisa *Braita*
excuse me, for the cooking. So we can't be talking about one
for making a fire. By the way, that's a good reason to
say the fire doesn't belong in that list regardless of this issue
of הויל *Ho'il*, right? The way we have the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*
says you get one set of lashes for cooking, one for making
the fire, but if you don't get separate sets of lashes on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, obviously that can't be the right read of
the משנה mishna, *Mishna*.
So how does that work with other types of עונשין *Onshin*? In
other words, let's say I steal something from you, then I put
it back in your house, then I steal it again ten minutes
later.
Well, stealing isn't a good example because you don't get מלקות *Malkut*
for it. But let's take an example of there's a famous משנה
mishna *Mishna*, if a נזיר היה שותה יין כל היום *Nazir haya
shoteh yayin kol hayom*. He was drinking wine the whole day. So
he only gets one set of lashes. But if basically they give
him separate warnings, separate התראות *Hatra'ot*. Say, don't drink. I don't care.
He drinks. Don't drink. I don't care. He drinks. So the separate
warnings basically serve to separate the acts as, you know, as different
acts. Distinct. Distinct acts. So here too, I mean it is true
that that could be the answer. The answer could be they gave
him separate התראות *Hatra'ot*, so you would get separate lashes same way
if it were the same. But again, the point of this משנה
Mishna's *Mishna* of how many sets of lashes is to give you
lashes for different איסורים *Issurim*, right? If the משנה Mishna *Mishna* or
the ברייתא Braisa *Braita*, if the ברייתא Braisa *Braita* wanted to say
you could get five sets of lashes for making a furrow, it
could have said yeah, you know, rather than something fancy that it's
כלאים *Kilayim* and שמיטה *Shmita* and all those things, it could have
said you dug a little bit and they warned you again, then
you dug some more, but that's not interesting. That's not what they're
looking for. They're looking for qualitatively different categories, not the same thing
multiple times because you had different
warnings. So הבערה *Hav'ara* doesn't belong there anyway, and even the attempt
to change it to מוקצה *Muktzah* and to claim that מוקצה *Muktzah*
is a דאורייתא *De'oraita* doesn't answer that question. So we still need
to replace הבערה *Hav'ara* with something else. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אלא Ella, אפיק הבערה *Ela apik hav'ara* fine, take out הבערה
*Hav'ara* making a fire, ואייל עצי אשרה *Ve'ayal atzei ashera*. And say
that we're talking that you're using the wood of an אשרה *Ashera*
tree, of a tree worshipped for עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*. And that
is lashes number five because you are deriving benefit by burning that
wood and by using it to cook even though you're not allowed
to cook, but okay, you're deriving benefit. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
ואזהרתיה מהכא *Ve'azharateih mehacha*,
the prohibition is from here, ולא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם *Velo
yidbak beyadecha me'uma min hacherem*. Nothing shall cleave to your hands from
the banned material. So that is a prohibition of deriving הנאה *Hana'ah*
from עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*. What? Very topical. Very topical. Right, good
point. Okay, so this the פרשה *Parsha*. ואמר ליה רב אחא בריה
דרבא לאביי *Ve'amar leih Rav Acha breih deRava leAbaye*, Rav Acha breih
deRava said to אביי Abaye *Abaye*, okay you think you've solved this
problem. You've dealt with הבערה *Hav'ara* and we didn't want to include
that because A, it's just an as we just got through saying,
you don't get separate lashes for separate מלאכות *Melachot* on יום טוב
*Yom Tov*, B, you know, this idea of הויל *Ho'il*, which is
what we started with hypothetically, the fire could have been for another
purpose. So you've taken it out and you've replaced it with using
wood of an עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*.
Which you think is a stronger reason for excluding הבערה *Hav'ara*?
Well, probably אין חילוק מלאכות *Ein chiluk melachot* if fundamentally you don't
have to start discussing this whole issue of hypothetically this, hypothetically that.
Fundamentally we're looking for different categories. And if the principle is that
by יום טוב *Yom Tov* we don't consider things different categories, that
seems to be a more straightforward reason. But that's debated, meaning here
we've just said you know there was an opinion that says you
don't consider those separate categories for יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Okay, so
the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. So it says to אביי *Abaye*,
right? Yeah. So the גמרא *Gemara* says ונילקי נמי משום ולא תביא
תועבה אל ביתך *Venilkei nami mishum velo tavi to'eva el beitecha*. But
there's a different prohibition by עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*, don't bring any
abomination into your house. So there actually are two sets of lashes
here and therefore that gets us over the limit. We were looking
for five. אלא אפיק הבערה *Ela apik hav'ara* fine, take out the
הבערה *Hav'ara* on יום טוב *Yom Tov* making a fire on יום
טוב *Yom Tov*, ואייל עצי הקדש *Ve'ayal atzei hekdesh*. you’re using הקדש
*hekdesh* wood, so wood that belongs to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*.
ואתת מהכא *ve-atat me-hacha*, and you learn it out from here: ואשריהם
תשרפו באש *ve-ashrei-hem tishrefu ba-esh*. You shall burn their אשירות *asheiros*, their
עבודות זרות *avoda zaras* with a fire, and the end of the
פסוק *pasuk* is לא תעשון כן לה' אלהיכם *lo taasun kein l'Hashem
Elokeichem*, but you don’t treat do this to God. Now, the simple
sense of the פסוק *pasuk* don’t do this to God means they
have their, you know, their temples and idols on all the hills
and all over the place. You, you only have one central place
of worship, right? כי אם אל המקום אשר יבחר ה' אלהיכם מכל
שבטיכם לשום את שמו שם *Ki im el hamakom asher yivchar Hashem
Elokeichem mikol shivteichem lasum es shemo sham*. Okay, but the דרשה *drasha*
is that here you learn out, and this by the way is
relevant to the issue of שמות Shemos *shemos* and destroying things with
God’s name on it, that you destroy עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, you
don’t destroy things with God’s name on it, you don’t destroy הקדש
*hekdesh* things. It is interesting because why don’t you also add the
prohibition of deriving benefit from הקדש *hekdesh* and the איסור *issur* of
מעילה *me'ila*? That’s not clear to me either. I mean, maybe it’s
to say it’s not benefit because in the end,
you know, you’re not allowed to cook and you’re not allowed to
benefit from what you did cook, but still, it is strange because
we quoted before the prohibition of deriving benefit from עבודה זרה *avoda
zara* and there does seem to be that there really is benefit
here. Anyway, you can transgress מעילה *me'ila* even without deriving benefit. So
it’s interesting that it’s satisfied with this answer because one could imagine
that you could have said that there are other prohibitions that also
need to be piled on here as well. Anyway, that’s the end
of the discussion of the ברייתא Braisa. *beraisa* that speaks about making
a fire and getting lashes for it, where the question was if
you hold of this idea of הואיל *hoyil* hypothetically, you shouldn’t get
lashes from making a fire because there’s hypothetical uses you could have
for the fire. Okay, so that is a דף *daf*, like what
was that, two דפים *dappim* or something, of, yeah, almost two דפים
*dappim* of this debate of רבא ורב חסדא *Rava ve-Rav Chisda* about
cooking from יום טוב *Yom Tov* to חול *chol* whether you get
lashes or not. Now we circle back and we tie it in
to our משנה Mishna, *mishna*. So let's take a look. אמר רמי
בר חמא *Amar Rami bar Chama*, so רמי בר חמא *Rami bar
Chama* said, הא דרב חסדא ורבה *ha de-Rav Chisda ve-Rabba*, that debate
of רב חסדא ורבה *Rav Chisda ve-Rabba* is מחלוקת רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer ורבי יהושע היא *machlokes Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Yehoshua hi*. That’s the
debate in the משנה Mishna. *mishna* of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, ורבי
יהושע *Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Yehoshua* where you have this חלה Challah *challa*
that’s טמאה *tamei*. What do you do with it? So רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says you bake it and then you make
it חלה challah. *challa*. And רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says you don’t
bake it, presumably you’re not allowed to bake it, and he says
but you don’t have to worry about it because it’s חלה challah,
*challa*, you don’t transgress for owning it on פסח Pesach. *Pesach*. So
how is that that debate? דרבי אליעזר סבר *De-Rabbi Eliezer savar*, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer* who feels you can bake it even
though eventually some of that bread is going to not be edible,
you’re going to have to call it חלה challah. *challa*, הוא סבר
*hu savar* אמרינן הואיל *amrinan hoyil* that we say הואיל *hoyil* since
hypothetically he says, look, hypothetically you could eat from any one of
those loaves of bread, or you know, you could be מפריש חלה
Mafrish challah. *mafrish challa* from each loaf separately and therefore every loaf
is edible, a little piece maybe isn’t, but again, since in theory
you could eat from any one of them, so the fact that
one is going to be forbidden does not mean that you have
done that you have actually transgressed because it is, you know, because
again, it’s not definitely that this one in particular you can’t eat.
You in theory could eat any particular one and therefore that’s enough
to say that it’s allowed. So that’s a similar idea of הואיל
*hoyil*, not exactly the same הואיל *hoyil* of, you know, guests could
drop by and the גמרא *Gemara* will distinguish it in a minute,
but it’s a similar idea. ורבי יהושע סבר *Ve-Rabbi Yehoshua savar*, and
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* holds לא אמרינן הואיל *lo amrinan hoyil*, we
don’t say הואיל *hoyil* and therefore I would not allow you to
bake it. There’s definitely going to be one that you can’t eat.
I don’t care that in theory you could eat any particular one.
One, there’ll definitely be one you can’t eat. You would transgress, and
I say though, don’t cook it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, just
have it become חמץ Chametz *chametz*. You don’t have to worry about
it anyway, it’s חלה challah. *challa*. אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*,
so רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said, ודילמא *ve-dilma*, maybe it’s not the
same debate. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer התם דאמרינן
הואיל *ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Eliezer hasam de-amrinan hoyil*, when does
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* say הואיל *hoyil* by baking all of those
loaves of bread and then you're eventually going to make one into
חלה challah, *challa*, אלא דבעידנא דקא עייל לתנורא *ella de-be-iddana de-ka-ayeil le-tanura*,
when you put all the loaves into the oven, כל חדא וחדא
חזי ליה לדידיה *kol chada ve-chada chazei lei le-didei*, I could eat
any particular one of them. Okay? So therefore I can say הואיל
*hoyil* because in theory I can eat any one of these loaves.
אבל הכא *aval hacha*, but in this case when you’re basically you’re
totally stuffed and you’re still putting food in the oven that you
are not intending to eat, דאורחים הוא דחזי ליה *de-orchim hu de-chazei
lei*,
it’s only fit for potential hypothetical guests that are not here and
are not coming. לדידיה לא חזי *le-didei lo chazi*, and for me,
I’m not planning and I have no desire to eat anything of
what I’m cooking, so then I might say אימא eima הכא נמי
Hacha nami, לא אמרינן הואיל *eima hacha nami lo amrinan hoyil*, maybe
you don’t say הואיל *hoyil*. Meaning the scenarios are different. Right, both
of them says hypothetically, but there might be different parameters under which
you can say hypothetically. It’s one thing to say, look, I want
to eat bread today. Every, I am putting all this bread in
the oven and I want to eat it or מצה Matzah *matza*,
whatever, and I want to eat it over פסח *Pesach*. This is
going to be our מצה Matzah *matza* for the סדר *Seder*. So
I’m doing it for the intention Whatever for tomorrow morning, whatever it
is, for second night סדר *Seder*, no that's anyway I'm doing because
I want to eat all this stuff. So the fact that there's
going to be one that I can't eat, I don't know which
one, that maybe is not such a big deal since fundamentally I'm
doing this in order to eat everything, you know, all the stuff
that I'm putting in the oven. That's not the same as the
הואיל *ho'il* when I have no interest in eating it today. I'm
not expecting guests, but I say since hypothetically if guests were to
show, this could be eaten, that gets me off the hook. That's
a different story. Maybe I don't go that far if I'm not
fundamentally intending to eat it today. So you can't say that the
חלה challah. *challah* case means he would agree by the case where
you're not really planning on eating it at all.
I've lost sight of the of the actual concrete facts of the
case. Is this baking מצה Matzah *matzah* for פסח *Pesach* יום טוב
*Yom Tov*? Yes.
You're baking מצה matzah *matzah* on יום טוב *Yom Tov* and but
you have to take one of them as חלה challah. *challah* which
you won't be able to eat because it's טמא Tamei. *tamei*, but
you haven't done that yet. So you're putting ten loaves in the
oven and you know that one of those loaves you're not going
to be able to eat, but you don't know yet which one.
You're going to designate it after. At the time you put it
in the oven, in theory, any particular one you could eat, or
nine out of ten of them you could eat, you just don't
know which one of them.
The rest is not going to be טמא Tamei *tamei*?
The rest is טמא *tamei* but you can eat it. It's not
חלה challah: *challah*. I mean it's not you know, so eating חולין
בטומאה betumah *chullin be-tumah* is not a problem. Right. Okay. So there
you could say there I could say הואיל *ho'il* because fundamentally I'm
baking now because I want to eat today. So that's okay. Oh,
one I won't be able to eat, as long as I don't
know which one, I'm not you know, I'm not clearly doing you
know, it's not like I'm taking one thing and doing an act
of cooking that I that I know is forbidden because I don't
know which one. That's different than when I don't plan on eating
today and I'm only going to get off the hook because in
theory somebody could drop by.
And why is the טומאה *tumah* piece, why do I need that
piece?
In other words, if it wasn't טמא *tamei*...
Because if it wasn't טמא *tamei* you could and it's
and a כהן *kohen* could eat it. So then I could be
מפריש חלה maphrish challah? *mafrish challah*. There's no there's no problem.
Ah, no one can eat it.
Here nobody can eat it because it's חלה challah, טמאה *challah tameiah*.
You can't eat it because it's טמאה *tameiah* so he can't eat
it.
He can't eat it. Ah, okay. And therefore what are you going
to do with it? Right? If you're baking it, you're cooking שלא
לצורך *she-lo l'tzorech*. If you don't bake it, it becomes חמץ chametz?
*chametz*. And that's the challenge. Okay, so just because you allow you
to bake there doesn't mean you'd allow to bake when it's not
for the purposes of eating today.
By the way, tell me this is a time people were somewhat
keeping הלכות טומאה וטהרה *hilchot tumah ve-taharah*, right? Because if we do
this today we're all considered טמא *tamei* anyway, right?
Right. I'll talk about today in a minute. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this: okay, אימא הכי נמי לאו מן הוא *Eima hachi
nami lav min hu*. אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי
*Amar Rav Sheshet brei de-Rav Idi* and רב ששת בריה דרב אידי
*Rav Sheshet brei de-Rav Idi* says: I'll challenge this comparison in the
other direction as well. ודילמא לא היא *U-dilma lo hi*, maybe the
argument that's saying that Rabbi Eliezer's הואיל *ho'il* by the חלה challah
*challah* wouldn't necessarily be the הואיל *ho'il* about the the guests. And
he says I'll say the same about Rabbi Yehoshua. עד כאן לא
קאמר רב יהושע התם *Ad kan lo ka-amar Rav Yehoshua hatam*,
when does Rabbi Yehoshua say that you can you don't say הואיל
*ho'il* and I won't let you cook bake the חלות *challot* since
one of them is going to be טמא *tamei*?
That's only התם *hatam* there דלא מנח הואיל אלא דאיכא חדא דלא
חזיא לא לדידיה ולא לאורחין *delo manach ho'il ela de-ika chada d'lo
chazya lo ledidei v'lo le-orchin*, because in the end one of those
loaves will be forbidden. Yes, I know you want to eat it
today, but at the end of the day one of them is
going to be off-limits to anybody. So there I'll say that will
really be a violation of יום טוב *Yom Tov* because objectively speaking
you don't know which one but you know that one will not
be able to be eaten and you'll have cooked it baked it
on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. אבל הכא *Aval hacha* in the case
of the potential guests דחזי מיהת לאורחין *d'chazi mihat l'orchin* everything is
theoretically edible. The problem is we don't have a hundred guests, but
in practice if we did, right, or in theory I should say
if we did have a hundred guests, everything would be edible. אימא
הכי נמי אמרינן הואיל *Eima hachi nami amrinan ho'il*, maybe here also
you would say הואיל *ho'il*. So he says look, you're right. There's
a similar type of an issue going on because you're baking these
חלות *challot* and you can't eat all of them. And do we
say well yes you can't eat all of them but in theory
you could eat any one. And that's maybe what the debate is
going on between Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua. But the גמרא *Gemara*
says it's not the same debate of Rabbah and Rav Chisda. The
difference is on the one hand the things that's better about the
חלה challah. *challah* case is you're fundamentally intending to eat most of
the loaves. The thing and therefore that might be an additional reason
to say it's okay. The thing that's worse about it is that
one of the loaves is objectively forbidden whereas in the Rabbah Rav
Chisda case everything is theoretically edible if you had the right number
of people, so the debate is not necessarily people don't take necessarily
the same positions. Okay. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרבי ירמיה ורבי זירא *Amru
rabanan kamei de-Rabbi Yirmiyah ve-Rabbi Zeira*. So the Rabbis said this in
front of Rabbi Yirmiyah and Rabbi Zeira, this idea that it's maybe
the same debate of Rabbah and Rav Chisda as the debate of
Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua.
They have the dough, why don't instead the piece they're going to
be מפריש maphrish, חלה challah. *mafrish challah*, right, before it smacks... Right.
They're going to put it all in the oven. Right. Why don't
they just take that piece
and set it on the side
or flush it down the throw it into the ים *yam*, throw
it...
מאי קסבר *Mai kasvar*,
throw it into the ים *yam*? And solve the whole problem.
That's an interesting question. Are we assuming דוקא *davka* according like that's
Rabbi Yehuda that אין ביעור חמץ chametz, אלא שריפה
*ein biyur chametz ela srefah*, which anyway on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
we actually say that he allows. other forms of ביעור *biyur*.
Like it doesn't have to be a problem. I understand he constructed
it.
Yeah, I'm wondering if that's different than the argument of תיתי לצונא
*titi l'tzona*
because you're saying if you don't burn it, it'll become חמץ chametz.
*chametz* whatever you do with it. If you're מפרר וזורה לרוח *mefarer
v'zoreh laruach*, the little pieces will still be, but the little pieces
will still be חמץ chametz. *chametz*. But you're saying, but then actually,
but fine, it's not different than if it was actually חמץ chametz.
*chametz* itself in your possession that you found on יום טוב *Yom
Tov* that you were מפרר וזורה לרוח *mefarer v'zoreh laruach*, that you
got out of your domain. Why does it have to be דווקא
*davka* through שריפה *sreifa*? That's an interesting question. I'll have to get
back, I'll have to see if people discuss that. That's an interesting
question. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara*, let's see where the גמרא *Gemara*
says. אמרו רבנן *amru rabannan* right near the square brackets, קמי דרבי
ירמיה ורבי זירא *kamei d'Rabbi Yirmiyah v'Rabbi Zeira*. So the rabbis said
it in the presence of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah *Rabbi Yirmiyah* and
רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*. They basically said,
you know, they said hey, you know there's this idea of רמי
בר חמא *Rami bar Chama*, that's the debate of רבא ורב חסדא
*Rava and Rav Chisda* is the debate of רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע
*Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua* in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
So רבי ירמיה קיבלה *Rabbi Yirmiyah kibel-ah*. רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* said,
oh, that's a good פשט *pshat*, I like that, ties in the
same debate. רבי זירא לא קיבלה *Rabbi Zeira lo kibel-ah*. רבי זירא
*Rabbi Zeira* said I don't buy it. Okay, so maybe for the
reason we said before that there's ways of distinguishing the arguments of
הואיל *ho'il* that just what the, that it's not necessarily the same
thing that's going on with the רבא ורב חסדא *Rava and Rav
Chisda* debate. So אמר ליה Amar lei, רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא *amar
lei Rabbi Yirmiyah l'Rabbi Zeira*, so רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* said to
רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*, מילתא דקשיא לן ואזא כמה שנין במאי פליגי
רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע *milsa d'kashyalan va-asa kama shanin b'mai pligi Rabbi
Eliezer v'Rabbi Yehoshua*. For many years we've been trying to figure out
what's at the core of the debate of רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע
*Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua*, whether you bake it and then make
it חלה challah, *challah* or whether you actually say you're not allowed
to do that but you don't have to worry because you don't
own it. Okay? We've tried to figure out like what's at the
core of that debate, why should you not be able to do
what רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* suggests and bake it and then take
חלה challah *challah* later? והשתא אמרו משמיה דגברא רבה Rabba *v'hashta amru
mishmei d'gavra rabba*, now we have in the name of a great
authority, of a very important authority, of רמי בר חמא *Rami bar
Chama*, who has told us a great way to understand this, that
this is the debate of רבא ורב חסדא *Rava and Rav Chisda*,
it's the debate of this idea of הואיל *ho'il*. ולא נקבלה *v'lo
nikableih*? And we shouldn't accept that? It's a great answer, why do
you always have to find a problem? אמר ליה *amar lei*, he
says היכי אקבלה *heichi akableih*, how do you want me to accept
that explanation?
דתנינא *d'tenina*, because we have a ברייתא Braisa *Baraita* that indicates that
that's not what they're debating, that they don't accept, that it's not
about this הואיל *ho'il* idea. How do you know this? Because the
ברייתא Braisa *Baraita* said, אמר ליה רבי יהושע *amar lei Rabbi Yehoshua*,
so רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* said to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, remember,
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* is the one that says that, you know,
just let it become חמץ chametz. *chametz*, it's not a problem. רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is the one that says bake it. So רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* said to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, הרי עובר משום
לא תעשה כל מלאכה *harei over mishum lo ta'aseh kol melachah*. How
can you say bake it? You're transgressing doing a מלאכה *melachah* for
something that can't be eaten. So that's his challenge. ושתיק ליה *v'shatik
lei*, and in this ברייתא Braisa, *Baraita* where we have this exchange,
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* doesn't defend himself, he's quiet. ואי איתא *v'ei
itah*, and if this really is that he holds it's allowed because
of the principle of הואיל *ho'il*, לימא ליה *leima lei*, why doesn't
he say back? טעמא דידי משום הואיל *ta'ama didi mishum ho'il*, so
defend yourself, say no, I allow it because I don't think it's
considered doing a מלאכה *melachah* because of this principle of הואיל *ho'il*,
that theoretically I could eat any loaf. So because he doesn't defend
himself to me that says that it's not based on הואיל *ho'il*.
I don't know what it's based on, but if it was based
on הואיל *ho'il*, then he would have defended himself and said that's
why it's allowed. אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said back to
him, ולטעמיך *u-le'ta'amach*, according to you,
that if there's silence it indicates that they, you know, that they
don't can't really defend their position.
Who's talking to רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah*?
So now רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* is talking back to רבי זירא
*Rabbi Zeira*,
right. Right, so he said according to you, הא דתנינא *had d'tenina*,
that which we taught in the ברייתא Braisa *Baraita*, the end of
the ברייתא Braisa *Baraita* says, אמר לו רבי אליעזר *amar lo Rabbi
Eliezer*, so רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* said back to רבי יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua*, like you could see this, you know, we have this sometimes,
you know, if you remember like a classic case is when the
blood of, for one application on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* gets mixed up
with the blood of four, do you do four or do you
do one? And I think it's also a רבי אליעזר רבי יהושע
*Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Yehoshua* there. And one of them says you do
one, the other says you do four, and he says, well if
you're doing four you're being עובר *over* on בל תוסיף *bal toseif*,
so the other one says, well if you do one you're being
עובר *over* on בל תגרע *bal tigra*. So it's the same type
of a thing here. He says, well according to you, you're being
עובר *over* on doing a מלאכה *melachah* on יום טוב *Yom Tov*.
So he said back to him, well according to you, what do
you think the according to you would be back? This is רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says don't worry about it, just let it become
חמץ chametz *chametz*. You're being עובר *over* on, yeah, you're being עובר
*over* on בל יראה ובל ימצא Bal Yira'eh u-Bal Yimatzeh? *bal yera'eh
bal yimatzei*. So that's what the ברייתא Baraita, *Baraita* says. He says
you're being עובר *over* on doing מלאכה *melachah*, he says you're being
עובר *over* on בל יראה ובל ימצא *bal yera'eh bal yimatzei*. ושתיק
ליה *v'shatik lei*, and he doesn't respond. הכי נמי דלא הדר ליה
*hachi nami d'lo hadar lei*? Do you think he doesn't have a
response to that challenge? הא קמהדר ליה במתניתין be-masnisin, *ha ka mehadar
lei b'matnisin*, we see in our מתניתין *matnisin* what his response is.
What does our מתניתין *matnisin* say the response to the בל יראה
*bal yera'eh* concern is? דתנן Ditnan, *ditnan*, לא זהו חמץ Chametz. שמוזהר
עליו משום בל יראה ובל ימצא *lo zehu chametz she-muzharan alav mishum
bal yera'eh bal yimatzei*. Says no, I'm sorry, you don't transgress בל
יראה ובל ימצא *bal yera'eh bal yimatzei*, it's חלה challah *challah*, it's
הקדש *hekdesh*, it's not yours, you don't transgress. So you see, even
though this ברייתא braita *Baraita*... The ברייתא, braita meaning the ברייתא is
stylized, right? It's very dramatic in the ברייתא if you don't know
the answers, right? If he says, hey, what about דאת דגמה לך?
Dat dugma lach? Hey, what about בל יראה ובל ימצא? So just
because the ברייתא doesn't have the defense, doesn't mean that a defense
doesn't exist. It's just sort of showing you what the competing arguments
are.
First of all, רב זירא Rav Zeira didn't quote the סיפא. Seifa.
What? רב זירא Rav Zeira didn't quote the סיפא Seifa of this
ברייתא.
I know, but that wasn't his interest, right?
And the second is he was taking on רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya
and that was like a major mistake.
Right, exactly. So anyway, so he says, so you see he has
an answer in the משנה. Mishnah דתנן, detnan, we have in the
משנה Mishna. לא זהו חמץ שאסור עליו משום בל יראה ובל ימצא.
Lo zehu chametz she-asur alav mishum Bal Yira'eh u-Bal Yimatzeh. אלא, what
do you see? שתיק ליה בברייתא, Shatik leh be-braisa, in the ברייתא
he was silent, meaning it's not necessarily a recorded transcription of the
actual debate, but the way the ברייתא is being written, there's no
response, okay? מהדר ליה במתניתין, Mehadar leh be-matnisin, the response is in
the משנה. Mishna He says you don't transgress. הכא נמי, so your
point was, when he says, oh you're doing מלאכה, he should have
said back, no, it's not מלאכה because of הואיל. So you know
what? אימא שתיק ליה במתניתא Eima shatik leh be-masnisa or במתניתין,
he doesn't have a response in the משנה, Mishna he doesn't have
a response in the ברייתא, fine. והדר ליה במכילתא אחריתי Ve-hadar leh
be-mechilta achriti and
in some other collection of Tannaitic material he has the response. Just
because we don't have a record of the response in this ברייתא
or this משנה mishna doesn't mean he can't defend his position. If
he really couldn't defend his position, he would have, you know, he
would have given it up, right? You have to have an answer
to 'what about the problem of doing a מלאכה on יום טוב?'
So just because he didn't say הואיל in any record does not
mean that that is not actually his position. So we have a
מכילתא Mechilta essentially. What? Yeah, a מכילתא Mechilta is a compendium, like...
We have something we call a מכילתא. Mechilta.
Right, מכילתא, Mechilta, which means... מכילתא Mechilta means, yeah, it doesn't mean
the מכילתא, Mechilta, מכילתא Mechilta just means a collection. ספרי... Sifrei... ספרא
Sifra is a book and ספרי Sifrei is a book. Like קונטרס?
Kuntres?
ספרא Sifra is a book,
the name of the different Tannaitic collections, מדרשי הלכה Midrashei Halacha on
the תורה Torah are basically very generic names. ספרא Sifra is on
ויקרא Vayikra which means book, ספרי Sifrei is on דברים Devarim and
במדבר Bamidbar which is books, and מכילתא Mechilta is on שמות which
means collection, okay? So anyway, yes, מכילתא Mechilta means a collection. Okay,
anyway,
so the basic point is he says we have a good way
of explaining the debate and just because hypothetically you could distinguish or
because you don't hear the answer in a ברייתא is not a
reason to throw out this great way of framing the debate. Okay,
so that's the issue, is it the same debate of רבה and
רב חסדא? So now the גמרא says like this: תניא ותנו בברייתא,
Tanya u-tanu be-braisa, רבי אומר הלכה כרבי אליעזר, Rabbi omer halacha ke-Rabbi
Eliezer, we rule like רבי אליעזר, which is that you bake it.
רב יצחק אמר הלכה כבן בתירא, Rav Yitzchak amar halacha ke-Ben Betaira,
we rule like בן בתירא Ben Betaira which is you put it
into cold water. And that is the end of that discussion, we
don't actually know what the הלכה Halacha is. Now if you look
at one line here in
תוספות, Tosafos, רבי אומר הלכה כרבי אליעזר, Rabbi omer halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer,
תוספות הרב יוסף פסק כרבי משום דקיימא לן כוותיה מחבריה Tosafos ha-Rav
Yosef pasak ke-Rabbi mishum de-kaima lan ke-vassay me-chaveira etc. רש"י Rashi also
has a discussion about how do we actually פסקן Pasken about how
to do this because we actually do have... we take חלה challah
nowadays and it is טמא. We always assume we are טמא. So
this question of how do you פסקן Pasken about this is very
relevant if you're making חלה... challah if you're making מצה matzah. on
יום טוב itself. And there's a serious discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim
of exactly who we rule like. Okay, now the גמרא turns on
to a related but not exactly the same discussion.
But that's essentially what we do, right? I mean, you know.
If you're going to do it, you take it... Forget about...
forget about like מצה matzah for a minute. Like say you're just
baking.
Yeah, then you take חלה challah and you burn it because we're
טמא and we burn it, okay?
Yeah, and we don't call חלה until we're done, is it for
that reason?
Yeah, but that gets into other issues of חלה בזמן הזה Challah
bi-zman ha-zeh and חלה חוץ לארץ Challah chutz la-aretz and so on.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא says like
this: וכמה שיעור עיסה? Ve-kama shiur issa? How much is the amount
of dough? Now this question really is not
about חלה בטומאה. Challah be-tuma. It seems to be the way רש"י
Rashi understands it, a general question of if you're making מצה matzah,
on יום טוב or on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, does it matter?
Really theoretically even ערב יום טוב. Erev Yom Tov. How much dough
can you make at any one time and not be afraid that
it's such a large quantity that it'll become חמץ? Chametz. Because you've
got to work it, you know, to keep it, you know, and
if you have a huge amount, you know, some of the dough
of this big lump of dough is not being tended to and
could become חמץ. Chametz. So what is the maximum size of dough
you're allowed to work with? We actually came up before, if you
remember, a long time when we're talking about like לחם עוני Lechem
oni and is it too big and so what is the maximum
amount of size you're allowed to work with that we won't have
חמץ Chametz concerns? And you'll see that the reason... second from לחם
עוני? Lechem oni? What? Yes, second from לחם עוני. Lechem oni. One
person. One person working. And you will see that the reason it's
related here is because there's also a minimum amount of dough in
order to be מפריש חלה. So where do those two things intersect?
Like is the maximum going to fall shorter than the minimum? You
know, are you going to be able to take חלה from the
dough? The dough you're making using for מצה matzah *matzah*. You could
propose. So let's take a look. All I know is on my
box of שמורה מצות matzos *shmura matzahs* it says on it מצה
matzah, חלה גענומען *matzah challah genomen*. So therefore we know that they
took חלה *challah* from there in terms of the question of the
minimum.
So let's take a look. I'm almost thinking that the amount you
can take is the amount that the maximum amount you can do
a מנחה *mincha* in because those are all מצות matzos, *matzot*. Unless
you say that's just by זריזין *zrizin* in the בית המקדש *Beit
Hamikdash*.
That's interesting. So let's take a look what it says. It says
וכמה שיעור shiur. עיסה *vechama shiur issah*. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר *Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
omer* בחיטים קבים kavs *bechitim kabim* or קביים *kabayim*. With if you're
using a wheat flour it's two קב kav, *kavs*, which is a
pretty large quantity. Basically the שיעור חלה *shiur challah* is as we'll
see is like a little bit more than a קב kav *kav*.
So and so
people know that and that שיעור חלה *shiur challah* is like forty-three
eggs' worth. Okay. So two קביים *kabayim* is about eighty eggs' worth
of dough, the volume of that. That's ballpark. So it gives you
a good sense. We're talking about a serious amount of dough. Okay.
Two קביים *kabayim* of wheat flour. ובשעורים *uveseorim* and barley flour שלושה
קבים kavs. *shlosha kabim* three קב kav, *kav*. Presumably that would not
that you know
barley doesn't ferment as quickly. רבי נתן אומר משום רבי אלעזר חילוף
הדברים *Rabbi Natan omer mishum Rabbi Elazar chiluf hadevarim*. It's the reverse.
Barley ferments quicker than wheat and therefore it's two for barley and
three for wheat. והתניא *vehatanya* didn't we teach in a ברייתא *beraita*
רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר בחיטים שלושה קבים
kavs, ובשעורים ארבעה קבים kavs, *Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka omer bechitim shlosha kabim uveseorim arba'ah kabim*. It's not two and
three, it's three and four. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא קשיא
*lo kashya*. It's not difficult. הא בכסיכתא הא במעליותא *ha bechasichta ha
bemaalyusa*. The question is whether it's inferior or whether it is or
whether it is
refined. If it's inferior then you can use more because in the
end the amount of actual flour that you're getting out of you've
got to get rid of all the I don't know all the
bran or all the dross or whatnot so in the end it
boils down to less if you start with the inferior grade. So
אמר רב פפא שמע מינה *amar Rav Papa shma mina* from here
we hear that גרין חיטי כסיכתא מחיטי מעליותא *garin chitei chasichta mechitei
maalyusa* that the degradation of you know of
of inferior wheat from from superior wheat is greater טפי *tfei* מגרין
שערי כסיכתא משערי מעליותא *migarin searei chasichta misearei maalyusa* from the relationship
of inferior barley to superior barley. Why? Because it went from four
and three to three and two. So the barley four bad equals
three good, whereas the wheat three bad equals two good. So the
what you lose in the wheat from the inferior quality is much
greater. דאילו התם תילתא *de'ilu hatam tilta*. There it's a
third. Three to two is a third of the three to get
down to the two so you lose a third. והכא ריבעא *ve'hacha
riv'a* going from four to three you only lose a quarter. Okay.
אמר רב *amar Rav* קבא דמלוגנא *kava de'melugna* this מלוגנא *melugna* קב
kav. *kav*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it's a name of a place.
But this קב kav *kav* this particular type of a קב kav
*kav* לפסחא *le'pishcha*. That's the amount. We've been saying two to three
קביים *kabayim* for based on wheat and barley and whatnot. He says
one קב kav. *kav*. If you're making your dough for פסח *Pesach*,
you're making your מצות matzos, *matzos*. וכן לחלה *vechen lachalla* and that's
the same minimum amount for making חלה *challa*. A one קב *kav*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says והתניא *vehatanya* or והתנן *vehatnan* didn't we
teach in a משנה mishna, *Mishna* חמישה רבעים קמח ועוד חייבין בחלה
*chamisha reva'im kemach va'od chayavin bachalla*?
Five רבעים *reva'im*.
A רבע *reva* is a לוג log, *log*. Okay. But it's a
called a רבע *reva* because as we say a quart. Okay. It's
called a רבע *reva* because it's a quart, it's a quarter of
a קב *kav*. Okay. It's a לוג *log*.
A לוג *log* is about fourteen ounces. Okay. So a קב *kav*
is about sixty-four ounces. Alright. So we say five רבעים *reva'im* so
which is one and a quarter קב *kavs* of flour is what
you're חייב *chayav* for a חלה *challa*. So what would that be?
Sixty-four I don't know how to whatever something like eighty ounces. Okay.
How much is a whole bag of flour?
Five pounds.
Pounds. Right. But ounces, well this actually is a volume measurement. Yeah.
This is a volume measurement. So I'm getting confused. But anyway if
you think about it's more than a bag of flour. Okay. It's
a lot. It's a lot. Okay. So anyway okay so these five
רבעים *reva'im* of flour plus a little bit is the minimum for
חלה *challa*. Now he said a קב *kav*. Now a קב *kav*
four רבעים *reva'im* is a קב *kav*. Right because a קב *kav*
is a quart a רבע *reva* is a quarter of a קב
*kav*.
Is he talking on דאורייתא *De'oraita* level or even דרבנן *Derabbanan* level?
This whole discussion. No.
There's no דרבנן *Derabbanan*. There's a minimum שיעור *shiur* for חלה *challa*.
We don't make a דאורייתא דרבנן *De'oraita Derabbanan* distinction. Okay.
So these days there
might be you might not be חייב *chayav* in חלה דאורייתא *challa
De'oraita* nowadays. A, it's חוץ לארץ *chutz la'aretz*. B, it's פוסט חורבן
*post churban*. But the size hasn't changed. Okay. So anyway so we
say that it's five רבעים *reva'im* and which is one and a
quarter קב *kav* and you're telling me it's one קב *kav*. So
הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar* so... So הכי קאמר, this is what he
means: קבא מלוגנאי, kava milugnai, this מלוגנאי milugnan קב, נמי אשיעורא קאי
nami achishi'ura kai is actually, you know, they did not have like
a bureau of standards, you know, with their measurements, and they had
different locales had different measurements. So this קב in this place actually
is a larger than normal קב, and actually is one and a
quarter קבים and is the size, the minimum size for חלה. Okay,
so anyway, according to him, what he says is the maximum that
you dough you can use for your מצות is also the minimum
that you need to take חלה, and it's one and a quarter
קבים. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said: הני נשי דידן, hani nashi didan, our women, okay, cause we
always, you know, when it talks about, you know, we mentioned this
before, the profession of making מצות, it talks about men bakers, but
when it talks about doing it in the domestic scene, it talks
about women. So anyway, our women נוהג למיפא כפיזה כפיזה לפסחא. noheg
lemifa kaphiza kaphiza lepischa. They bake like little, little amounts for the
for the מצות, and רש"י Rashi says this כפיזה kaphiza is three
לוג, okay, which is three quarters of a קב. We've been saying
two קבים, three קבים, even the most recent thing was a קב
and a quarter. He says our wives do very small amounts to
be very safe, they only do three quarters of a קב at
a time. Meaning they shouldn't take or don't have to so they
won't take חלה. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי
said back to him: מה דעתך? ma da'atach? What what are you
thinking? לחומרא? lechumra? You want to be strict, to be extra safe
that it doesn't become חמץ? Chametz חומרא דאתי לידי קולא הוא. chumra
de'ati lidei kula hu. It's a חומרא chumra that turns into a
leniency, דקמפקא ליה מחלה, dekamaphka lei mechallah, that you're being strict by
פסח, but you're getting out of an obligation of taking חלה. They
don't have to do
it unless there's a certain amount?
I understand, but but meaning, if under normal circumstances you would make
more, you would normally make a large amount and take חלה, and
you're going to say, no, you should only make half, we have
to be strict for פסח. Well, what you're telling me to do
is to do it in a way that I'm not going to
be taking חלה. So he says, you know, that's not an acceptable
trade-off. אמר ליה דעבדינן כרבי אליעזר. amar lei de'avdinan keRabbi Eliezer. No,
I'll tell you we solve that problem, we do wind up taking
חלה. How do we do it? We follow what רבי אליעזר says,
a different רבי אליעזר, not the רבי אליעזר of
our משנה, mishna דתנן, we learned in a
משנה mishna in חלה: רבי אליעזר אומר הרודה ונותן לסל, Rabbi Eliezer
omer harodeh venoten lasal, even if you kneaded the dough separately, if
when you take it out of the oven, you put all the
loaves into the same basket, הסל מצרפן לחלה. hasal metzarfan lechallah. The
basket combines them. So yes, there's a minimum amount, but you can
get that minimum amount even if you did not make that amount
of dough together. You right? Michael and I or whatever could be
making at separate tables, making separate loaves of bread, and with separate
pieces of dough, and neither one is the size for חלה, and
we all put it in the oven, and when we take it
out of the oven, we put it into the same basket, that
creates the minimum size. Yeah, that's what they do in the מצה
matzah factories. Right. Is the minimum size just for like I would
assume the minimum they just bring in the minimum size to say,
like, oh, if you're making like a tiny bit of dough, then
that's fine, you don't have to do any הפרשת חלה, hafrashat challah,
so we're just going to make this minimum size. So I don't
understand why they could just take it anyways. What are you saying?
One more time? Even if they're even if they're making the minimum
for חלה is a huge amount. 43 eggs, as you point out.
Right. Right. But so they're so they're doing three-fourths of a קב.
So why can't they just take it anyways? Oh, why can't you
be מפריש חלה? So that's because there's no it's not like for
it wouldn't be חלה. Meaning, if there's no חיוב חלה, chiyuv challah,
it's not like, oh, you don't have to, but you're allowed to
take it. It's like it's an all-or-nothing. If you don't have the
minimum size, you don't take חלה. But that's what I was saying
before, that the minimum size, I would think is just a minimum
size to say, this is when you're doing something significant, so now
we're going to make you do it. In contrast to say you
don't have to do it. No, there's no like option. No, no.
There's no option if you do less. It's like, let's say I
eat in a סוכה sukkah and I go and I drink water
in a סוכה, sukkah, right? I don't get to make the ברכה
beracha of לישב בסוכה
leishev basukkah because it's not the מצווה mitzvah
when it's not
that when it's not those parameters. But these days we do bake
less and take חלה, isn't that what we do generally or not?
That what? We bake less than the amount? We might do it
because we don't know exactly, you know, then there's also issues of
חלת חוץ לארץ chalat chutz l'aretz and זכר, zecher, but it's not
really the מצווה. mitzvah. And also the question about exactly how you
define the שיעור. Right. So you're saying it's okay? Like we do
it? No. Let let's not worry about it, okay, right now.
The basic point is that there's no two sizes.
If it's less than the minimum,
you don't מפריש, you don't make a ברכה. beracha. What we do
nowadays is more complicated because it's בטומאה and it's
חלת חוץ לארץ chalat chutz l'aretz and so on. So anyway, the
גמרא says like this. So, okay, ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Va'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הלכה כרבי אליעזר, halacha keRabbi Eliezer, we rule
like רבי אליעזר. So no problem.
We'll be able to have our חומרא, chumra, everybody will do a
small amount, but we'll put it all in the oven and take
it all out in the same basket and therefore that'll make the
minimum and then we'll take חלה then. אמר ליה, ואיתמר עלה, ve'itmar
alah, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, לא
שנו אלא ככריות של בבל, lo shanu ela kekicharyot shel Bavel, when
do we say that if you bake them and take them out
of the oven That they basically like bite one another, meaning you
know, right, that when you buy those like חלה rolls on שבת
at, you know, they're all connected to one another.
So fine, if you made separate loaves, but you put them in
the oven next to each other so that when they expand, they're
actually connected to one another, then you can say that they combine
in the oven or in the basket and that you could be
חייב בחלה chayav in challah that way. אבל ככחין לא, Aval kakhin
lo, but ככחין, kakhin, which apparently are more like רש"י describes it
more like, what do you call those like long stick-like things? Baguettes,
right, which are, you know, which anyway the way they're located and
the way they bake is they don't expand into one another and
they remain separate. So that won't work. So it, you know, it
won't work here for to get to a חיוב חלה. chiyuv challah.
Only it'll only work if you're making certain types of loaves. Also
remember, by the way, they're making מצה. You know, you think about
rising, expanding. Again, you have to really think about like the תימני
Teimani type of, I mean like the, you know, the like the
פיתה pita type of מצה to even begin to get an image
of this. Or maybe that's his point: you're making מצה, it's not
going to expand so they're not going to touch one another in
the oven. So the גמרא says הא איתמר עלה נמי, Ha'itmar ala
nami, it was said on it, אמר רבי חנינא: Amar Rabbi Chanina:
אפילו ככחין, afilu kakhin, it applies even to these baguettes. They don't
have to touch in the oven and they can still combine when
you put them, when you take them out of the oven and
put them all in the same basket. I'd like to see what
that מצה looks like. Okay. בעי רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmiyah, now
רבי ירמיה asked this idea that when you put it in the
basket, the basket combines it. By the way, I should say what's
also not clear to me, תוספות Tosafos discusses this as well, is
what role does the oven play? Let's say we bake them in
separate ovens but we put them in the same basket. Is it
that they were in the same oven and the same basket? I
mean at one point the גמרא thinks they even have to touch
as they're baking. So even when it says they don't have to
touch, do they also have to be in the same oven? Anyway,
now the question is about this idea that the basket combines them.
טבלא שאין לה לבזבזין, Tavlah she'ein lah levazbezin, thank you, לבזבזין, levazbezin,
if you have a טבלא, tavlah, you have like a flat, a
flat vessel that does not have a lip around it, does not
have a rim. It's just completely flat. Like, you know, think about
like a חלה board, okay, that would be a good example. You
have a flat חלה board, מהו, mahu, what's the story? תוך כלי
בעינן, Tokh kli ba'inan, does it need to be in a vessel?
והא לא, v'ha la, it's not in, it's on the board, it's
not in a vessel. So therefore they're not combined because it's not
held by the walls of a vessel together. או דלמא, O dilma,
or do we say, אויר כלי בעינן, avir kli ba'inan, they have
to be in the airspace of a vessel? והאיכא, V'haika, and it
is, it's all on top of the board even though it's not
held by the board. תיקו, Teiku, we don't know the exact definition
of what does it mean to be combined by the, by the
basket. Is it like that big flat paddle that you see bakers
use when they take things out? Maybe, that could be. That flat
paddle, you know, also in pizza places they have. Yeah, something like
that. Right, it's true because a חלה board isn't big enough to
hold things. But right, if you thought of, but no, but I
don't think it's just the act of taking it out because you
wouldn't take out all that in one time. But if you thought
of more like think about like if you had a flat pizza
tray, although that does have a tiny little edge. Cooling racks, they
put them on racks. Or something like that, like a cooling rack,
that would be a good example, right. You know, right, when you
go into the bakery, right, you see all these things on these
cooling racks. Right. So if it doesn't have a lip but it's
all on this flat rack, is that enough to combine them? Okay.
תניא, Tanya, we turn to a ברייתא, רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer
omer: הסל מצרפן. hasal mitzarfan. רבי יהושע אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua omer: התנור
מצרפן. hatanur mitzarfan. So רבי אליעזר says it's the basket, רבי יהושע
says it's the oven. So again, the question is, the one who
says basket, is it basket and oven? The one who says oven,
is it only oven not basket? But okay, we don't exactly know.
רבי שמעון בן גמליאל אומר: Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel omer: כככרות של
בבל שנושכות זו מזו מצרפות. kikarot shel bavel shenoshkhot zo mizo mitzarfot.
And he says again, this is so this is a nice תנאים
Tannaim that we've sort of referred to earlier. He said it's only
the Babylonian ones that actually touch one another or, you know, bite
one another when they are, when they are expanding in the oven.
So that was a little interesting digression about, A, talking about a
חיוב חלה, chiyuv challah, which is, you know, the משנה כיצד מפרישין
חלה בטומאה, keitzad mafreshin challah b'tumah, and B, the minimum amount of
dough you should be dealing with when you're making מצה, which somewhat
relates because it gets into discussions about the minimum amount that you're
חייב בחלה. chayav in challah. Okay. In that topic of baking מצה
in a way that won't become חמץ, Chametz. almost that discussion we
had before was almost more relevant to this next משנה than it
was to the previous משנה, because let's look now at this next
משנה. ורבן גמליאל אומר: V'Rabban Gamliel omer: שלוש נשים לשות כאחת ואופות
בתנור אחד זו אחר זו, Shalosh nashim lashot k'echat v'ofot b'tanur echad
zu achar zu, that you can have three women that are all
making using the same oven. Now they would have small ovens, so
basically what it means is you've got three women all doing, you
know, all in synchronized, everybody's kneading the dough, everybody is patting down
the dough, then it comes time to use the oven, we say
take a number. So basically what he says is is that you
can actually have two of the women waiting for the third one
to finish baking, and we're not afraid that the dough will become
חמץ. Chametz And while she's still working it? Not exactly clear, okay.
So and we're not afraid it'll become חמץ. Chametz? Let's see what
the response is. וחכמים אומרים, Ve'chachamim Omerim, the חכמים Chachamim say, שלוש
נשים עוסקות בבצק כאחת. Shalosh Nashim Oskot Bebatzek Ke'achat. No, no, no,
they can't be doing it simultaneously. They have to be doing it
like, you know, at an assembly line, sequentially. Okay, אחת לשה, Achat
Lasha, one is kneading, אחת עורכת, Achat Orechet, one is like, you
know, shaping it and patting it and banging it, which is the
stage after the kneading, ואחת אופה, Ve'achat Ofa, and the other is
baking it. So basically they're like on an assembly line, so when
the one is done baking, then the next one gets their dough
in and the next one moves down on the line, but nobody
is waiting. Everybody is at a stage of the process, nobody is
waiting to use the oven. Okay, and because if you wait, if
you wait, it'll become חמץ. Chametz. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva Omer,
Rabbi Akiva says, לא כל הנשים ולא כל העצים ולא כל התנורים
שווים. Lo Kol Hanashim Velo Kol Ha'etzim Velo Kol Hatannurim Shavim. You
can't have a rule about this. Not all women act, you know,
make, you know, do with the same degree of efficiency, not all
of, not all woods are the same, some take longer to light,
heat, some, some take, some take a shorter amount of time, not
all the ovens are the same. This is with the 18? זה
הכלל. Ze Haklal. No, again, because remember what we, the whole discussion
in the משנה and the גמרא is a non, it's a very
fascinating, it's non-quantified, right? It's all about looking at the dough and
seeing if it has signs of being חמץ. Chametz. One little discussion
in one גמרא said if you have no other way of determining
by observation, 18 minutes. Okay, we have completely quantified this. Okay, and
this is exactly what's going on in this משנה as well. The
first two opinions are trying to quantify. Oh, it's okay if you
only have to wait for two other women to finish. Actually, it's
not okay, you have to do assembly line. Rabbi Akiva says who
can make a rule about that? Every case is separate about how
whether it's becoming חמץ Chametz. or not. So what do you do?
I assume, in general, if you can quantify something, it's more true.
Well, it's certainly easier to apply and it's more right. I think
there's a deeper feeling of if you can quantify something, then there's
an objective way of determining, objective and it's truer. Right, it's in
case law. Right, exactly. So Rabbi Akiva says you cannot quantify this.
זה הכלל, Ze Haklal, this is the rule. תפח, Taphach, if it
starts expanding, תלטוש בצונן, Taltosh Betzonen, so you smack it with cold
water to stop it from expanding. Observe and you take a look
if it's becoming fermented. So like we said before, cold water, have
it take a cold shower and then you move on. Okay. תנו
רבנן, Tannu Rabbanan, we taught. Now this is going to talk about
how the assembly line does. Does it לשה, Lasha, woman number one
is kneading, היא מקטפת, Hi Mekatefet, she moves on from her station,
maybe I'll say from station A to B to C, okay? We
have three stations. If you think about it like that, right? Here's
the oven with the fire going in. Okay, here's station A and
here's station B and here's station C. Station A is, I don't
know how to show it, with the hands and the kneading. Okay,
station B is with like, you know, the hitting down of the
dough and the smacking of it, the dough. Okay, and station three
is, and station C is the fire, okay? So woman number one,
so it says, so here's what it says. It says, תנו רבנן,
Tannu Rabbanan, לשה, Lasha, the one who's kneading, היא מקטפת, Hi Mekatefet,
she moves to station, she moves to station B to do the
hitting of the dough and the smacking down of it, וחברתה, Vachaverta,
and then her friend, woman number two, moves into לשה Lasha into
the kneading station, לשה תחתיה. Lasha Tachteha. Then מקטפת, Mekatefet, that after
she's done with station B of smacking down the dough, so מקטפת,
Mekatefet, where were we? היא אופה, Hi Ofa, then she moves to
station three to do the baking, וחברתה, Vachaverta, her friend who was
here at station A, מקטפת, Mekatefet, moves to station B תחתיה, Tachteha,
תחתיה, Tachteha, she takes her place. Right, it's a shift. It's a
rotation. וחברתה, Vachaverta, and then the third person who we haven't mentioned
yet, אופה, Ofa, and then the third, I'm sorry, no, no, והשלישית,
Vehashlishit, the third one, oh wait, והשלישית לשה Vehashlishit Lasha then moves
into station number A. Okay, והשלישית, Vehashlishit, והשלישית, Vehashlishit, fine, אופה, Ofa,
לשה. Lasha. אופה, Ofa, now the one who had been baking, היא
לשה, Hi Lasha, she moves after she's done baking back to station
A, back to doing the kneading, וחברתה אופה, Vachaverta Ofa, the one
behind her moves from station B to תחתיה, Tachteha, moves from station
B to C, she goes from from the banging of the dough
to the baking. והשלישית, V'hashlishit, the third one who had been kneading,
מקטפת, mekatefet, she goes to station B, she goes from the kneading
to the smacking of the dough. וחוזרת חלילה, V'chozeret chalila, and you
continue in this cycle. So basically you've got a, you know, you've
got an assembly line and everybody is moving from one station to
the next. This was before who was it in the industrial age
that figured out that for greater efficiency is to have one person
just stay at their one station? Ford? What? That was Ford, wasn't
it? Okay. It certainly but but it totally undercut worker satisfaction with
their job because you never got to go through you know do
the whole process. Anyway, so that's what you're having. You're moving through
the stages. כל זמן שעוסקת בבצק, Kol zman she'oseket babatzek, and this
is the very important principle, as long as the dough is being
worked, אינו בא לידי חימוץ, eino ba lidei chimutz, it cannot ferment.
That is used. That means it's not just about time. It's about
time when you're not working it. As long as you're kneading and
working the dough, there is not a problem of it becoming חמץ.
chametz. רבי עקיבא אומר לא כל הנשים. Rabbi Akiva omer lo kol
hanashim. Rabbi Akiva says you cannot have any rules here. תניא, Tanya,
תנא ברייתא. tana baraita. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, said Rabbi
Akiva, דנתי לפני רבן גמליאל. danti lifnei Rabban Gamliel. I, you know,
had the following discussion in front of Rabban Gamliel, who Rabban Gamliel
by the way was the one who said that he was the
one that was very lenient. He said you could have two women
waiting to use the oven. I said ילמדנו רבינו, Yilamdenu Rabbeinu, teach
us our master. בנשים זריזות או בנשים שאין זריזות? binashim zerizot o
binashim she'ein zerizot? This is like the sort of, you know, the
naive way of challenging a question. He says I don't understand this.
Are we talking about, you know, very, you know, very not fastidious
but what's the word anyway efficient women or not efficient women? בעצים
לחים או בעצים יבשים? be'etzim lachim o be'etzim yeveshim? Are we talking
about about you know wet you know wet sticks or dry sticks?
And then of course you could imagine the next question. Dry, okay,
how dry? Super dry? Somewhat dry? Right? בתנור חם או בתנור צונן?
b'tanur cham o b'tanur tzonen? Is it hot or is it cold?
Hot, how hot? Right? אמר לי, Amar li, he said to me,
אין לך אלא מה ששנו חכמים. ein lecha ela mah sheshanu chachamim.
So all you have is what the rabbis said. זה הכלל, Zeh
haklal, this is the rule. תפח, Tapach, if it starts expanding, ותלטוש
בצונן, v'tiltosh bitzonen, put in cold water, which sounds like he got
Rabban Gamliel to agree to him. Right, it wasn't just I disagreed
with Rabban Gamliel but I sort of you know asked these innocent
questions to him and he wound up agreeing that there's no real
rule. תפח, Tapach, תפח. Tapach. It was like תפוח. Tapuach. Yeah, yeah.
תפח, Tapach, ותלטוש בצונן. v'tiltosh bitzonen. That means that's not before it
starts to be חמץ. chametz When it starts it's already חמץ. Something
is happening. No, no, but that's the next משנה. It's the process
is beginning but it hasn't yet hit critical mass. But it's interesting
that there is that moment, right, where you see it expanding but
it's yet to become חמץ and you can catch it at that
moment. And let's just at least read the next משנה because the
next משנה is that exact point. Which Rabban Gamliel was this? Ah,
it's not the first. No, it's got to be right because it's
the same period of Rabbi Akiva. Okay. שאור, Se'or, now שאור se'or
is not שיאור. si'or. שאור se'or sourdough, שיאור si'or which we discussed
earlier was the dough that has begun to ferment but has not
yet hit full חמץ status. ישרף, Yisaref, it has to be burned.
ואוכלו פטור, V'ochlo patur, but if you eat it you're exempt. It's
not yet biblical חמץ. Now, what about the ותלטוש בצונן? v'tiltosh bitzonen?
It's too late at that stage. This is after the תפח tapach
stage. This is when it actually fermenting begins at the point that
it's too late, at least rabbinically. It's not biblical, at least according
to one opinion. סדוק, Siduq, now סדוק siduq once you start seeing
the cracks, ישרף ואוכלו חייב כרת. yisaref v'ochlo chayav kares. You have
to burn it and you get כרת. karet? So when the actual
moment of חמץ is not the expanding, but when the cracks appear
on the surface. איזהו שאור? Eizehu se'or? Now what is the שאור
se'or that's this middle stage, forbidden but not yet biblical? כקרני חגבים,
Kikrnei chagavim, small little cracks like the horns of grasshoppers, like you
know little little branching cracks. That's still not yet biblical but it's
forbidden. סדוק, Siduq, now what is סדוק siduq which is the cracks
that it's biblical חמץ? שנתערבו סדקים זה בזה. Shenitarvu sdekim zeh bazeh.
You see a crisscrossing of the cracks. That's biblical חמץ. דברי רבי
יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So again, if it starts expanding you can
arrest the process by cold water. Once you see cracks it's a
rabbinic problem. Once you see crisscross that's biblical חמץ. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim
omrim, the חכמים chachamim which you'll find out in a minute is
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, say זה וזה האוכלו חייב כרת. zeh v'zeh
ha'ochlo chayav kares. No, excuse me, even the little cracks is biblical
חמץ. ואיזהו שאור? V'eizehu se'or? What is the שאור se'or which is
an earlier stage? כשיכסיפו פניו, K'sheyichsifu panav, if it's if the faces
are blanched, like turns crusts, כאדם שעמדו שערותיו, k'adam she'amdu searotav, like
a person whose hair stands on his head, you know his face
blanches. So again expanding is still not yet a problem. Turn pale
color. A pale color. A pale color. Expanding you can arrest it.
When it becomes a pale color or begins to crack, it's rabbinic.
And when you have criss-crossing or certain amount of cracks, it's biblical.
Let's just take one more minute and finish the דף, very easy,
here's the next few lines. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: איזהו שיאור, eizu
se'or, what is שיאור? se'or? כל שיכסיפו פניו kol sheyichsifu panav כאדם
שעמדו שערותיו. ke'adam she'amdu sa'arotav. Again, if it's blanched, it's שיאור. se'or.
סידוק, siduk, once it starts cracking כקרני חגבים. kekarnei chagavim. וסידוק, v'siduk,
okay, that's שיאור se'or which is only rabbinic. סידוק siduk which is
biblical, that's כקרני חגבים, kekarnei chagavim, that's like the grasshopper's, a little
bit of cracking. That's דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So what
in the משנה was the חכמים, Chachamim, in the ברייתא is רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But even the little bit of cracking is already
biblical. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim of the ברייתא is
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the משנה, which is more is more
lenient, says no. איזהו שיאור eizu se'or כקרני חגבים. kekarnei chagavim. שיאור
se'or which is rabbinic, that's the little bit of branching, like the
grasshopper antenna. סידוק, siduk, the cracks which are biblical, that's a further
stage. That's שנתערבו סדקים זה בזה, shenitarvu stakim ze baze, the criss-crossing
of the cracks. וזה וזה האוכל חייב כרת. v'ze v'ze ha'ochel chayav
karet. But for both of them, you get כרת, karet. which is
wild, because we've always said that the earlier stage, right, the so
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the grasshopper stage is פטור. pator.
והנן תנן v'anan tnan שיאור ישרף והאוכלו פטור דברי רבי יהודה. se'or
yisaref v'ha'ochlo pator divrei Rabbi Yehuda. This is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda distinguishes between the grasshopper and the criss-cross. But
he says the grasshopper stage is פטור. pator. How come here it
says כרת? karet, So אימא לרבי מאיר זה וזה האוכלו חייב כרת.
l'Rabbi Meir ze v'ze ha'ochlo chayav karet. What it means is, according
to me, the grasshopper stage is still only rabbinic. But according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, whether it's the grasshopper stage or whether it's
the criss-cross stage, for him both of those are biblical and both
of those you get כרת. karet. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא,
מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir? What's the reason of
רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? אין לך כל סדק וסדק מלמעלה, ein l'cha
kol sedek v'sedek milma'ala, you don't just get a little grasshopper crack
at the top. You have no little crack at the top of
the surface שאין לו כמה סדקים מלמטה she'ein lo kama sedakim milmata
that does not have a lot of cracks going on below the
surface. So basically what we see is that there are three stages:
expanding, you know the process has begun but you can arrest that,
you can throw it into cold water; blanching, a beginning of a
crack, and multiple cracks. Everybody agrees multiple cracks is biblical חמץ. Which
of the earlier stages, the blanching and the little cracks, does it
become does it become חמץ or not? That is debated, but there's
a middle stage where it's not כרת, karet. but it is at
least rabbinically forbidden. And I'll just remind you, when we discussed the
issue of cosmetics, we discussed שיאור se'or and חמץ נוקשה, chametz nuksha,
and also the possibility that this might that there might be a
middle stage which might even be biblical, might be a חייב לאו,
chayav lav, but might not be כרת. In our משנה we don't
see it; in our משנה we see that there's either rabbinic or
it's כרת. We don't see a middle stage of a biblical prohibition,
but we did have that before. Okay, very good.